the
welcome i will start english because marshall
wants to continue on english don't know
what i will try to
and abroad to present marshal because
you can eighty have a very long
and warm relationship and we will continue
on this boss and i am very
interested in
yeah well in their stock
to or any non dutch speakers otherwise
it can be in dutch with i
guess alexandre you can understand it or
totally does
beth so-so if if if there are
questions in dutch it it's fine but
i will i will do it in
english showa welcome all
yes today is about a cautious coast
two point oh and it's extra assured
of a second episode of the talk
i held two years ago so it's
a bit of a stepchild between then
and now
this assert this is me i work
for eighty computing i'm going to go
owners and director of the company and
in the past six years i have
transformed from a normal guy to an
absurd nerd so it's a bit more
technical than it used to be before
but i have a lot of fun
working at a company and working together
with a great team
so yeah a bit about me and
about eighty computing we were founded back
in nineteen eighty five the founders actually
here in the in the room and
it's now part of what's called to
their group which is a group of
trading providing companies
we provide training as well and also
consultancy and we do only open source
technology so a linux and everything above
which evolves infrastructure as code containerization etc
so we have a strong focus on
devils and bathroom engineering and this is
some of the tools we have for
expertise
so we also developed some some learning
paths which are visible at our booth
so if you like it please drop
by and this is this is what
we do and what our core businesses
and this is also the reason why
i'm here today because the way we
develop our training courses has changed quite
a bit over the last couple of
years
and i would like to take you
along a bit of a journey how
we got to the point we are
today
so to get started we will travel
back in time because it's now twenty
twenty four and i was here two
years ago in twenty twenty two and
one of the slides i showed back
then was this one and this was
basically the id we had back then
so we said well if we have
a training course why why
don't we see it as being an
application which is written in some form
of goat and with some automation like
she actually pipelines we can deploy that
goat and thus the training inside an
online learning platform and this id was
filled in with some tools so we
said well we are going to write
to the courses in restructured text we're
going to build a container that's transforming
the source code into what's called artifacts
so it can be a pdf it
can be html or it can be
an e-learning package which there are two
main open standards for which is eight
five b and
scorm they both are some kind of
archive type of package which contains all
the relevant content for delivering an e-learning
and back then we had the idea
that we would use moodle which is
an open source learning management system or
lms and use that as a as
a provider for
one or many other lms us to
actually display the course content to the
user or the trainee
and the reason to use a new
spring which a proprietary lms is because
we already used it back then in
our group of training companies so it
made sense to say well let's use
what we have and build something before
it to actually automate it so this
was the idea back then and we
had a bit of this income stopped
working so we had to restructure that
parts are working and some get applied
pipelines but that was about it so
there was nothing functioning on that date
but
we had a goal and that is
that we wanted to change the way
we use hands on training laps during
our courses because that's one of the
big parts of our training that you
actually do some exercises in the hands
on level five minutes to get acquainted
with technology
then since gulf times there is a
virtual classroom so if we have a
classroom training there's not only a physical
an option to attend but you can
also join online and the third is
that we have the course content as
i just mentioned that was like the
first starter can we automate the way
we produce the course content and deliberate
part way
and the way we do it today
is that we from eti computing have
built our own custom cloud lips so
it's based on virtual machines which are
deployed with terraform in google cloud and
if you join a training of course
you're using the leps from a from
a browser and it's it's working pretty
fine but it has some drawbacks when
it comes
to speed of deployment and flexibility
for the federal classroom we are up
to date use go to trading which
is also a proprietary solution it works
perfectly fine but it's a separate system
and for the core software as mentioned
of course contents it's a new spring
which is used to deliver the workbook
for the industry
concerned nowadays
and the hottest thing for attendees is
this all these three tools have their
own credentials so if you want to
lose the lap you will have username
and password if you want to use
the online session you will have the
online classroom you will have username and
password and if you're going to use
the of course content that's is a
separate system with a separate username and
password you can in
imagine that there are some people less
chevy with this kind of stuff than
others so it takes around thirty minutes
to get a classroom up and running
because somebody loses an email containing the
credentials or they do not understand which
system is what so that's a big
struggle for our our customers
so
and other trends why i'm here again
is that our customers say we don't
want classroom training only we want what's
called blended learning and that's why the
blender is here nobody knows exactly what
it is but everybody wants it and
you can see it as a mixture
of different types of learning methods so
it can be partly gloss
from training but also learning and maybe
also some training on the job or
something like that and the combination is
what's called blended learning and this means
that the the need for us to
automate and be more flexible has increased
because we see an increased demand for
customers to say i don't want classroom
training only i want a mixture but
i want your code
then because you will deliver great content
so we deliver have we now set
a new goal and the new goal
is that we combine the lips the
course content and the virtual classroom altogether
in one lms and as you can
see it's moodle so we are focusing
to make everything work in moodle which
is the open-source elements and i will
drop by
why we made this choice but in
the end for the customer it means
they will only receive one set of
credentials if you can log into moodle
you're good to go and everything else
is within the elements
and to get there we've come a
long way but also we've come pretty
far and this is a timeline of
what we had to endure between the
last time was here and now
so in january two thousand and twenty
three which was right after the presentation
we started working with a group of
four people on like the first iteration
of this id so we actually started
building and we used moodle esa as
our lms and together with a new
spring as mentioned and we still used
the vm labs
so they are used through apache guacamole
which enables it to make a streamer
for a full browser base to use
and that's how we could deliver a
desktop experience or a terminal emulator and
you can use the lecture that way
so this was the first try but
we bumped into quite a lot of
issues mainly on the new spring site
because the api i was not working
as we hoped so i talked to
the developers for new springs at bulk
we want a ph that have posted
requests so we can upload content automatically
and configure courses automatically it was all
impossible and they did not have it
on the roadmap because there was
for their situation no business case to
implemented because they say well you want
to develop your course content in our
platform that's our business model we said
well we're not going to do it
we want to have our own of
course development and we want your platform
just to play it out but not
to develop your platform so that was
quite a bitch
challenge to see can we work around
it and still use a new spring
but it turned out after two months
of trying that it was not really
feasible so we had quite a bit
of a disappointment because we could not
make it work because there was a
too little openness of the of the
apia
then in the summer
we struggled still a bit with it
so we had done some research on
additional
the looks on other lms if that
were available remarks you can we work
around it but we soon noticed noticed
that a lot of lms us have
this shame and proprietary limitation so there
are only a few lms us that
have an open ai which you can
create content cautious of course contend with
and one of them is
and it's maybe a bit of a
of a dragon of a product but
it can do everything you want to
do and it has a ph for
everything so it's really open and really
flexible so the big choice we made
in the summer so we're going to
drop into spring it's not the way
forward for us and we're not going
to use it and the fun thing
is
that's after we decided to drop a
new spring within two weeks we had
actually a running concept because now we
knew we were going to use moodle
and we can start to integrate some
other things because we do not need
to worry about another platform that's that's
going along with this also during the
same time we dropped the the old
fear-based laps
and we went to contain a base
left and we started using that's the
icon there google cloud run which is
their simplest container runtime mo service so
she can we use the same lap
concept and run electrical diner because the
startup time is way way better than
for vms and this way after summer
we had a
our first version life so we had
an lms with course content and with
lapsed at work container based animals integrated
so you can use the laps from
from moodle and with this this version
we actually shipped a pilot to a
customer and they did so much from
illinois we did and we're pretty satisfied
with the learning experience so we were
on the right track but we also
noticed that we had some limitations because
google cloud run is quite limited with
what you can do it in the
container so root privilege it's elevated extra
system the running services running containerized workloads
in the container it's all not supported
and that is what we need for
three
many quarters because we have a docker
of course and it will be quite
hard to use docker without a being
able to use docker
so that's why in january we did
another iteration another sprint of development and
we said well we're going to use
communities as a platform for our trading
laps and that means like a second
complete redesign of our functions but now
we had a good direction so we
had a lot of
experience in the meantime we knew moodle
back and forwards up to the source-code
we we understand how the system works
so we knew how to solve certain
problems and with cuban eddies which now
runs on an gk even in the
community scouts will we ever hosted kubernetes
cluster we can now run all kinds
of workloads based on on cuba
eddies which in a voss also nested
containers etc
and this means that we now have
version two point oh and that's why
i'm here again because we have had
some cool work who stuff and now
we can say well we nailed it
the the direction we have chosen is
the right one are we going forward
in this day in this direction
now you see a strange b that
comes up and that's part of a
of an ecosystem i will explain that
later on because that's a tool we
developed in-house to make this all work
so what does it look like
we actually built everything being a git
repo so we use git lab as
an git repository and in the git
leper environment for every training course there
is a repository and as repository contains
everything that's needed for a training course
so that means ever
the thing is there for the workbook
for the exercises but also for the
lips and with a push towards the
the repo a pipeline is triggered and
as will deploy the lips we deploy
the hiv packages to moodle so it's
all in one repository it's all code-based
so it's truly cautious growth and i
will hopefully have a working demo on
how it's all
coconuts
so as mentioned this does not work
out of the box so we do
from the start had to division that
if there is a two on the
market available we will use it and
we're not going to develop it on
our own but in the end you'll
end up developing on your own so
that's what we did and we have
created three tools three separate tools
the first one to show scottish then
we have the sphinx and proctor which
is to beat at you so sure
before
so kuch this is what you use
as a course developer and it's an
acronym for a course it's called trading
update software and it's it's what you
use when you create a new trading
or where you want to work to
test your training locally and it's a
created especially to make the whole process
more human friendly because without the altitude
two it involves a lot of creating
repositories creating ship modules and gets complex
stuff and this two of the way
the second two is an add on
to the existing sphinx library that's python-based
to a text processor and this is
what we use to make sure that
everything we write in our social source
code is converted to a working training
package so we have decouple
old the source code and the templating
for instance so this makes sure that
the source code gets in a nice
layout the way we wanted to to
have look and feel but it also
means that if we change a branding
or we want to have a white
label aversion that we can that can
create it from out a sphinx this
also has some custom directives because we
have
quite some specific needs for instance how
are you going to integrate a lap
so we created a custom directive for
it so you can just type that
you want to lap and the software
will know what you mean and will
render it
now this this is not really funny
after nimble to the image issue is
a bit of a joke but the
sphinx is an existing too but we
adapted it
that was an all things now
and the third and last one is
maybe the most important and it's called
proctor and this is actually the two
that does quite a lot when it
involves the denzel let because it takes
care of authentication so it makes sure
that if you have an account in
moodle and you are enrolled in a
given course that you also can do
the laps
so it connects moodle and an the
the the authentication from proctor so that
you do not have to log in
again and that it stays up to
date that you have actually rights to
use the leftists evolved also it provides
a dashboard so that you can check
if a lab is running or you
can start one an instantly today
tested or to see if everything you
say is working so that's a that's
a nice feature for for development but
it's also done with her with proctor
and under the hood it uses a
key cloak which is an open-source an
altercation or two to make sure that
everything ft works and this evolved quite
so much development because we wrote a
custom plugin for moodle but also
also contributed to a plugin for authentication
that was already there but had some
less elegant solutions in it so we
pushed it back to the developments that
well be i think we improved the
deployment
what prosor also does is the lep
orchestration so it actually talks with the
kubernetes cluster and starts jobs and every
training has it's own unique jobs so
this way you talked to proctor and
say i want to lab proctor says
to communities start this leapt with this
specification and it will pop up
and this is done by a config
file so every training course repo has
this a jamo stellt coffee and this
is actually a lab definition so you
could say i want a lap and
this should be the name of the
lap it can consist of a single
container or it can consist of multiple
danish so this example is for a
docker lap but you have a registry
container an additional container so you can
push and pull images from from one
to the other within one lap and
this should make sure that the proctor
knows what to deploy an incumbent elissa
on the hood
and as mentioned we use communities and
the reason is not because we are
the biggest fantasy of community because it's
so easy but because it can do
a lot on an issue and so
there is for our use case not
truly an alternative that s the same
flexibility and same options so
so a running near vm stuff root
access etc it's all possible and communities
and we did not found any other
solution with the same support an ecosystem
so this is a a high level
design of how this works i'm not
going to step through it in in
too much detail but we have as
mentioned a gcp managed control plane and
we run a couple of notes that
dynamically scale up different workloads depending on
what your needs are and if necessary
if we have a
a lot of concurrent chinese it'll scale
out automatically to make sure we deliver
what's what's needed and we use the
google cloud secret manager for all secrets
to use of it's mainly integrated in
the google ecosystem but that makes it
easier from a management perspective because we
have a third form a template that
can redeploy the complete environment when needed
so it's it's all infrastructure as code
for the for the platform itself
let's see for the rest there is
nothing truly special about the design this
is a pretty textbook stuff and best
practice when it comes to networking but
we have some awesome specific to stick
to to make sure these work so
we need external dns because every lap
should be
available to the internet so we need
unique your else so we use this
this to to make sure that every
lab gets a unique euro that's resolvable
to to the cluster
also we use shut miniature to make
sure that all the leps are
dispatch with tls so there's encryption not
in place it's not and we do
not have any special data about disaster
it's nice to do and it prevents
warnings in the in the browser
also where we as mentioned do a
lot for also read the first one
was the secrets operator and that's is
what i mentioned we use a google
c to a secret engine but we
have a plugin on communities to interact
with it and this is for dns
so we every lab has it's unique
dns entry
ingress is done by the engine extra
ingress controller and last but not least
we use a special runtime and that's
called chatbox chatbox is an open source
project that enables you to run system
d workloads and near vm experiences on
kubernetes show it's an alternative
to cryo or owls whose goals i
believe contain a d which is also
runtimes for our communities but we use
this box for for our desired workloads
and as mentioned proctor our special orchestrator
for for this so if the democrats
are a bit well willing i will
show how this works in practice so
what i'm going to do is here
life create a new training course from
scratch so there's nothing running now and
let's see if we can get it
working
ng
let's see
alright so i'm in a directory here
and what i'm going to do is
use your cactus so uncles a cactus
create an eye for sneak because i
do not nautical ments all my heart
let's see
i'm not a machine but this a
creates a new course
so i will explain what it does
it will say create a new course
choose a language which is english or
dutch give it a release or initial
initial release give it a title and
give it a unique name so in
this case i will call it an
aloof and that's all i need to
do and a cactus now we will
create
in the back everything that's needed for
our trading skeleton
so here we go it will clone
some awesome default some templates or repositories
of a burp yeah it is complains
a bit i'm not saying we are
bug free but it's a it's working
and now this is a this is
get lap if i refresh the browser
we now see that we have a
new trading gold and luke
and there is some templating already in
the in the repo and now we
have a basic scaffolding for it for
the trading so you see the conficker
file weird so read me there's a
makefile for for building the lab and
now we have our our course in
a hit
but we still need to do something
else and that's that we need to
add a topic or a chapter to
the course so
of course normally in our classrooms reservation
is built up around chapters unification yes
and doesn't matter in this case shoot
the students should have met her i
guess
yeah i could try it it will
it will fail probably if it's not
working it might be two things it
works or it will say you're not
in the right directory so let's see
about what i'm going to do now
is to add a new directory or
a new show technically it's a short
module with a new in this case
a new topic and this is called
zero on the demo this is the
name of the topic but it can
be anything else and i referring to
a specific branch here and that's because
version three point o is our stable
branch and that makes it work so
let's see what it does it's a
you're right
so this should work
so now it's closer the the the
chapter or the topic of repo and
now if you go back to kit
and go to docs and refresh it
there should be
another
i dunno it's it's true yep it's
a bit quirky but now i have
to
to push it to to edit
so i need to add the new
module to it
the first commute
and push it
we're still working on like this flow
to have some extra arguments for cactus
that this is done ultimately but now
it shoots contain
mom can do it yes there it
is so now the shop window is
connected to the course and we have
have our trading
up and running so now i need
to copy some some stuff so i
will make sure i'm in the right
directory
and what i'm going to do now
i prepared a small coffee file i
will copy it and i prepared a
small demo course which i'm going to
copy and
this otherwise would have taken a lot
of time
why is it not working
michigan
two
she
should be
cannot stand my eyes and working
she
yep
hmm
now it's working we need to edit
again
the roach and confused
in addition to going to work
i need to edit here too
show first push the shipping will do
vertical mirror for this one
our second commit we are this is
a sub module this is the first
one
let's see an hour to two days
and coffee
can we get any names
hello
i need to type it right
alright so now we have our scaffolding
for for training and let's see what
it's what it looks like so we
have this just like our course based
directory and this contain said the the
getting up cfl but this only contains
a reference to a default pipeline that
said we didn't get lap so not
every training has a unique
a huge pipeline fell but it only
refers to a standard pipeline we have
in and get left so we have
a separated the infrastructure part from the
course development part so that as a
trainer if you are developing the of
course it's more of a creative process
you need to worry as little as
possible around older infrastructure and stuff that's
needed on the on the background so
there is a separate team working on
the infrastructure and a separate team working
on the course content
then we have to convert film and
this contains all the settings that we
require for our training course so in
this case it will take contain a
trading gold trading name the language and
in this case an h five b
settings so we can decide if you
have a simple question should it contain
the answer or not so you can
use it
as as a quiz or you can
use it as a as an xml
for instance so these are all settings
that you can adapt and as you
can see here there's also a lecture
directive that's defining what the left should
look like while base image the original
dockerfile to restore to use and in
this case there will be a demo
rockefeller to build to the library environment
so within the docs directory there is
the demo directory and there's the rst
file so this is actually the course
content so now we have a slight
which has hello all and there is
a multiple choice question in here there
is an image and here there is
ilab so this is accustomed directive this
is all you need to do to
say i want a lap here and
put it in the inequality
and of course we have a left
directory and that contains an example dockerfile
i'm not going to show the demo
dockerfile because it contains some stuff that
makes you able to to change the
outcome of your trading so what it
looks like it's just a normal dockerfile
so there's nothing special here it's just
a dockerfile and it contains
some are special think so
we copied the home directory where you
can put the exercises in and we
copy if you have a test so
you can test your lap and we
use technical mumbo to check if you
have done something if it's actually working
so that is also copied and we
run some post install script to make
sure that the settings from the lab
are all defined as as we need
so this should be always your rockefeller
but for the rest you can build
custom images you can do as everything
you would normally do with with docker
in this case i have written some
tests so this is just a shell
script are doing some muslim actions and
changing some checking showing muslim values and
this is actually the way we we
write a check it's it's called best
units which is a besh based testing
framework so in this way we can
let see what the desired outcomes should
be
and if it corresponds with what you
have done in the in the lab
and and also there is a home
directory is here and just to show
that it's a unique directory this contains
fl company named hello
andalusia aspects fixing it so just to
show that it's a unique lap
alright so now we have everything up
and running and all the rest all
the other files are just necessary for
making this stuff works i'm not going
to talk in detail because that's all
the infrastructure stuff that's a that's a
geostationary you do not have to worry
about it as a as a traitor
but we can have some some fun
with this because i now have this
trading and i can use
this
two lens to see if everything is
is good so now it's it's working
so this training course has fell it's
a syntax so they're enormous no mistakes
in it but if i now for
instance a let's see in the coffee
diaper something here
again it will produce an error who
say well there is something wrong with
your visual foul because i expect this
these failures and you have something else
so this is really helpful from a
software development perspective that you can test
locally if your syntax is a is
ok before you push it to the
to get regular
so it should be find out and
the same goes for the hsbc index
if you mess up a directive it
will produce an error so this has
served us political and what i now
can do is use a local version
of the out a sphinx to actually
make
this training course so i'll now building
it and i can use it locally
it's bills
it's called phoenix so now i've built
the e-learning course locally and i can
use leumi which is an open source
tool for viewing hsp or auditing and
now i have my training course so
this is a working learning containing the
the picture i can provide an answer
check it
and i also have my lepanto here
with the question
but the laps do not work locally
this way because of altercation etc i'm
not running running kubernetes nor proctor but
you can see that it's detecting there
should be a lap here
so this is really powerful that you
can offline completely on your laptop check
if everything's working
but what is also possible
is if we go to the
the next directory i can run the
laps locally so i can loose i'm
using padma that also works with with
docker
i have to come on here this
easier
to be here
true to do
that works quite well up to now
so our drinks to probably
yep i can just use the dockerfile
and build it locally so i'm using
the demo dockerfile and do not show
what it actually does because of her
secrets that it contains but i'm taking
it with the luke and now it
shoots to build it and i can
run it
so there we go it's now running
and if i open a browser locally
and i go to the port i
published that now we have a trading
lap running containerized on our laptop so
this way you can also test all
the training exercises locally on your laptop
just in your browser so i
prefer written the test script which was
cold and aloof and i can show
it this contains the demo directory
which contains the hello file and if
i got it it says in luke
shaw everything we have defined isha is
there but as mentioned i've written a
test so if i now say check
with test it will provide an answer
but i have not done the exercise
yet so this is the wrong answer
but if i now run the script
to test it which was cold and
aloof
it will now create that directory and
create a file that wasn't there before
and it will say the correct answer
should be this answer so now we
have tested the lep exercise and we
know that it's actually executable that are
no mistakes and that it actually performs
the way we expect it to to
perform so now if i again run
the check command
it will provide the correct answer because
we now have actually done the exercise
and this is all done locally so
this prevents a lot of pulling and
pushing towards get left because you can
just dessert and push it back then
so this looks pretty good so now
we have working of a coarser content
we have a working lab and now
we can push it to
to to get lip but before we
do are any questions so far
yes
i'm going to show it because uh
yeah there is a lot of this
debate and discussion but in anti computing
whether to use them or not because
they're quite complex abstracts they are bitter
and friendly sometimes but
i will show it immediately why why
we use it and why it's fun
let's go back to the
train the directory yep
the reason why we used to use
this is because we can do this
we can add another topic but not
a chapter from a completely different rating
so in this case i'm going to
add it my and luke training course
a directory from our python threading which
is a completely different rating but it's
also gets something to do so if
i do this
is when our clone it into the
docs directory and now i have zero
too and this has the same structure
this is a bit of a different
training so it has some more stuff
to it but this is now added
to my content so if i go
back to this directory and create a
build directory
and create a trophy again
there we go
a b produce some warnings but that's
not too bad i now am i
build directory f
zero two
it's a second chapter
and there we go now we have
python training as part of our training
course so this is the reason why
we use automobiles because if we have
a customer that says well i want
some topics from this writing have some
topics on the training we can now
say well aware this is your menu
choice just edit and
render a completely unique new e-learning
meaning
yes guess it's a bit of an
idealism because you need to make sure
that this course content has like a
head and a tail on it's own
because if it's a ongoing story it's
pretty hard to say well i want
the middle part but it's technically feasible
and especially if you're having
in some smaller topics you can conduct
an own unique trading pretty easily this
way so this this is why we
why we use it and how we
use it
guess
nope we've dropped by
because they upload a pretty badly
but the fun thing is that also
this a training course contains a lap
so i'm not sure if it's here
i don't know the course
my top of my mind but there
should be also if if there's leps
in this course it should also work
because it's part of the of the
course
alright so now i need to add
this to the repo so good and
dogs
and it's commute again
and biotin
bush and now switch over to get
that because now there should be pipelines
running
where is it here
there we go so it's now running
a pipeline i see it filled not
sure why but we'll see
and this actually is a now failing
orleans
that's interesting why is it
it's a demo
unable to access it has some permission
issues going to have one quick look
might be that at the the module
is one
the privates should be internal i guess
this is annoying
we came pretty far it should be
internal i guess
i will run it again to see
if this assaulted
let's see
run again
there you go
if it survives linting face it should
be fine
because everything else we have tested locally
and hit repos testing locally is a
bit hard to it now produces a
warning which is
all right so complaining about summer some
layouts or stuff so that's not a
breaking change i guess
or breaking a thing it's still running
so this this is good this is
good so what i will do in
the meantime is show you our this
is our testing environment for our moodle
environment so this is actually moodle and
we've customized it to a bit for
look and feel but i already created
an aloof demo where trading
of course and this will contain the
the h five p in a bit
so we will have to wait for
the pipeline to where to run if
are any questions in the meantime please
feel free it will take a couple
of minutes
it's it's done through the pipeline so
the pipeline connects to the the the
moodle a b i and will upload
the hiv
now it's a hsp it's just a
package for moto moto has the capabilities
of displaying a trophy it doesn't need
to know anything else so we will
see how it's how it works but
now if the pipeline is completed it
will
it's taken quite long show
might be that the user information that
we fished or it's building the laps
now so
it's now building the container left but
it will push the d h five
b to the to the test environment
and disaster at the dashboard i mentioned
and if i refresh it it should
contain the luther lap within a couple
of minutes
it's taking a bit long
you can do it
it's always quick when you don't need
it
go on
while we have five minutes left shower
there is already the the demo created
i'm not sure if it will run
because it's still creating but proctor knows
that the lab has been edit
yes
and as far as i know it's
a bit out of my comfort zone
but i think it's wonky cloak instance
which is referred to with it's synced
with the moodle accounts
yes just
let's see it's not doing anything yet
so the lepage center there is a
bit annoying that it takes so long
because there's normally it goes faster it's
now says that it should be there
so let's go back and refresh this
alright
i started
yes so now it's a actually from
the dashboard deploying the new let we
created so the stakes are because it's
now actually deploying on the kubernetes cluster
twenty seconds ish tool to deploy that
up there it is and now we
have the lab running and if you
opened it in the browser it will
work it will work the reason
i did not have to authenticate is
because i already locked in to moodle
so it uses a cookie and is
already knows that i'm enrolled in this
course that i have the permission to
use the lab but if you open
this on your own laptop it will
say it will show up the the
locking screen like we saw in the
in the local demo
let's see is it finished
it's failed
oh no why did it feel
i feel to build a comp the
contents and that's a shame but i
have an older version already here so
this is what it should look like
a let's see now it's not there
maybe there's an older version that i
can use because this is where you
actually connect the hf befell to the
trading course so here
search the package and i can delete
it because we have a placeholder and
now there should be an aloof
there it is maybe there's an old
version because i've already tested it's a
couple of days so it's a shame
fell
now if a display it you will
see the same content that we saw
locally here it is so now it's
in our learning platform and we can
use it to ship to wear to
our customers and here you can see
there is a lap and it's also
knows that i already have a leapt
for this training running so this is
the same lap as here so if
i say hello
you see hello here so it's it's
the same connection
yes we do and it has technical
reasons i'm not too aware of but
we tested the last of this works
best with key strokes and this kind
of stuff because we had some trouble
and that's possible because you have to
shame the shame you out so i'm
actually now this can be the traitor
from the dashboard and i can have
the same session as the twenty so
that's possible because if i go back
to the dashboard i can see one
the active leps here so i can
just join us
so while i'm looking with you now
that's why this one of the main
reasons we have the dashboard as well
too for student support yep so now
i can run the same script and
it should work because we tested it
to already offline
so now we have in our lms
our open source lms completely as course
built of course that didn't exist before
the session and now russia is life
running in our learning platform it's all
open source based and we also have
the ambition to open source the tools
we developed in-house to if you would
like it
i can build this yourself or with
some some additional knowledge of communities google
cloud and as she actually pipelines
all right so we have one minute
left but that's not too bad because
the last two slides are are a
roadmap we have still some challenges
maybe ish
as you have seen it's still has
some rough edges we still need to
polish on things we also have some
challenges when it comes to a persistency
and startup times of the lips so
weird a tweaking to make them even
faster and also if you're taking a
course of multiple days it would be
nice that you have persistent data between
the first second and third day
so that has some challenges for some
muslim laps and also we have some
worries about realistic real to real-world scenarios
for terraform and ansible how are you
going to deploy a real resources or
provision so muslim infrastructure and also how
are we going to run kubernetes winning
communities to host our communities training in
this
leps as well so we're not there
yet but we can do docker we
can do that didn't show with but
we can run nested containers and have
a docker leper in in this distribution
as well so it's pretty cool and
we are looking at two feared to
see if we can make things even
even better
and from mortal course site and we're
trying to ultimate as well the course
creation in moodle because i've done it
by hand now but we are writing
our own terraform
plugin devil can talk provision of course
in moodle fire terraform so that's a
that's on the roadmap and also we
have some issues with reporting scaling also
web to the teaching this idea to
our colleagues from other companies that are
a bit less less tech savvy his
challenge to to say that this is
quite elegant and andy
so we have some awesome things to
do
but there were making steps and we
have also under meanwhile contributed to quite
some open source projects because we fixed
bugs we found some interesting quirks and
features so it has been a great
journey to where to get where we
are
alright any questions i think we have
zero seconds left
yes got one sorry
yes it does pdf html hiv and
maybe some other formats as well yep
any other questions
i can i can i can shoot
so the question was how does a
big blue button for the federal classroom
fit in this is actually something i'm
not sure if it's in a test
environment
it's integrated as well with the within
moodle so we are going to run
a pilot's course this week
where is it's i think here
yep so this is just a topic
in a moodle and this is the
virtual classroom so if you join session
here you will go to the physical
classroom so it's all integrated in the
institute
alright i'm here for the rest of
today so if you have some questions
left but thank you for attending the
thank you